<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An history of the transactions betwixt the crown of England and the states of the Netherlands since they first began to be a republique to this day shewing the most remarkable occurrences not onely betwixt them and the Spanyards and how far the English engaged in their defence but also all the chief proceedings betwixt them and the English both in matters of War and Trade.</title>
            <author>W. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65526</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13506444</idno>
  <idno type="VID">99816</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240859477</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6851</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13506444</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65526)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99816)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 480:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An history of the transactions betwixt the crown of England and the states of the Netherlands since they first began to be a republique to this day shewing the most remarkable occurrences not onely betwixt them and the Spanyards and how far the English engaged in their defence but also all the chief proceedings betwixt them and the English both in matters of War and Trade.</title>
                  <author>W. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Mabb for Edward Thomas ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: W. W.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99816:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99816:1"/>
            <p>AN HISTORY OF THE Transactions Betwixt the Crown of ENGLAND And the States of the NETHERLANDS, Since they first began to be a Republique, to this Day. <hi>Shewing the most remarkable Occurrences not onely betwixt them and the</hi> Spanyards, <hi>and how far the</hi> English <hi>Engaged in their Defence, but also all the Chief Proceedings betwixt them and the</hi> English, <hi>both in matters of War and Trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Thomas Mabb</hi> for <hi>Edward Thomas</hi> at the <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Little Brittaine,</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:99816:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99816:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Pistles like Prologues of Playes, being for the most part past over without Reading; I shall not therefore Enlarge my self, only to give you an Account, that I have in this work used my best Endeavours to be punctually True in these Collections; The Work it self would have afforded, matter sufficient for a Large Volume: So many of our Noble Hero's having been Engaged in their Service, and many of them lost their dearest Lives, in that Nations Defence, dying there in the Bed of Honour. Yet am I confident no matter very materiall is here omitted, and therefore free from those many Impertinencies with which Large Volumes must needs be stuffed. This may serve to give sufficient Instructions to the Intelligible Reader; like a little Watch shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time of the day, as well as a great Dyall; and therefore more usefull, because less combersome. Here hast thou truly presented
<pb facs="tcp:99816:3"/>(and not in a Multiplying Glass) the great kindnesses the <hi>DUTCH</hi> have from time to time received of the <hi>ENGLISH;</hi> And on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side, how unthankfull the <hi>DUTCH</hi> have been for them. What my performances have been herein, I shall neither Extenuate nor Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll, leaving every Reader, to judge as he best pleaseth; But this let me tell thee, if thou beest a True <hi>ENGLISH-MAN,</hi> thou canst not but in reading it, very much rescent the Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Affronts which the <hi>ENGLISH</hi> have continually received from that Nation. I shall not add hereunto by way of Aggravation, nor reflect upon the Visitation of the Almighty so hevy now upon them; no less then add of <hi>1000</hi> dying of the Pestilence at <hi>AMSTERDAM</hi> in one Week: A True <hi>ENGLISH</hi> Nature, as he hates Ingratitude, so doth he scorn to insult over Men in misery. My Prayers therefore shall be, that the Almighty would be pleased to remove his heavy hand of Visitation from them, and that they would call to minde the great benefits they have received from the <hi>ENGLISH,</hi> and that Ingratitude is the worst of Vices.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A True Lover of his Countries Honour, <hi>W. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99816:3"/>
            <head>An History of the Transactions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and the State of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> since they first began to be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique. Shewing the great benefits they have received from the <hi>English,</hi> and their many neglects therein.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O begin with the first Rise of the <hi>Netherlandish</hi> State, who knows not with what Tendernesse, and upon what Terms they were first taken into the bosome of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> for after the Death of <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Castile, Aragon, &amp;c.</hi> and Lord of <hi>Belgium;</hi> a Prince of great Magnanimity and Puissance: <hi>Philip</hi> the second his Son succeeded
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99816:4"/>him, who transported with Ambition, and a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Zeal, (the Reformation of Religion begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning then to grow to some strength in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try) he resolved to subject them to his will and pleasure: These Countries at that time, by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of former Princes enjoyed very large Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges and Immunities, of which, for the better Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrating the matter, we shall give you the heads of some of the chief:
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Heylins</hi> Microcosde of the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands.</hi>
               </note> 1. That the Prince should place no Stranger amongst them with Jurisdiction over their Estates and Persons in Offices of War, or Justice. 2. The Prince could give nothing to the Clergy: Nor 3. levie any Subsidies without the States of the Country; with several other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, too many here to recite. These large Privileges King <hi>Philip</hi> thought too good for so mean a people as he esteemed them to be, besides his Zeal to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> from which they now were falling; He therefore resolved to reduce them by <hi>Spanish</hi> Rhetorick (<hi>viz. the Sword and Cannon</hi>) and to that purpose sent the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> with a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>issant Army to be his Vice-Roy amongst them, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him Commission to place and displace at his pleasure, and to Execute any that he found op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite to his designes; who having setled himself in the Government, quickly deprived them of their large Liberties, by taking away all Authority from the ordinary Courts of Justice, and Erecting new Consistories; Several of the Peers he Condemned and put to Death, of which the two chief, were the Counts of <hi>Horn</hi> and <hi>Egmont</hi> whom he beheaded,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99816:4"/>Garrisons of <hi>Spaniards</hi> he placed throughout all their Cities and Villages, built up diverse Castles, and by Force Exacted of them the twentieth part of the Fruits of the Earth, and the tenth of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vables upon every Alienation: He also brought in the <hi>Bloody Inquisition,</hi> and did behave himself so Tyrannically, that the People were indeed truly miserable.</p>
            <p>Yet some there were that scaped his hands, of which number was the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and <hi>Count Lodowick</hi> his Brother, who endeavoured what they could in Defence of their Country, though not with such fortunate Successe as they expected, for though notwithstanding many Papists as well as Protestants joyned with them (it being a War of <hi>State</hi> and not of <hi>Religion</hi>) yet Duke <hi>Alva</hi> was so Potent, they could not perform much that was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable.</p>
            <p>Not long after Duke <hi>Alva</hi> (whose Tyrannies had made him justly odious) was called home, and <hi>Don Lewis de Requisens</hi> was appointed Governour in his stead;
<note place="margin">Stows An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls.</note> During whose Rule many of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> abandoned their Country, some flying into <hi>Germany,</hi> others into <hi>France;</hi> but the greatest part of them into <hi>England:</hi> After his Death, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and his party began to recover some strength and courage; But quickly after, <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Austria,</hi> the Naturall Son of the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth was sent Governour, with a very large Commission, and great Authority; With this <hi>Don John,</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> often Negotiated
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99816:5"/>on the behalf of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> who promised fair although it proved but meer dissimulation, which she well understood, though she seemed to take no great notice of it, and therefore to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine him, she underhand cherished the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> as much as she could without breach of Peace with <hi>Spain,</hi> and permitted (if not sent) many <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> to go over to their aid; amongst whom was <hi>John Norris,</hi> second Son to the Lord <hi>Norris, Henry Cavendish,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Morgan</hi> Colonels, with seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall other Eminent Persons, who performed many notable services to their eternal Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Don John,</hi> whose ambition first gaped for the Kingdome of <hi>Tuness,</hi> and afterwards for that of <hi>England,</hi> by the Marriage of the Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> then Heir to the Crown,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Martin</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </note> being disappointed of his aspiring thoughts, died as it is conceived of meer grief; in whose room was <hi>Alexander Farness</hi> the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> made Governour of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> by the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> under whose Government the People were brought into worse case then ever; so that perceiving themselves too weak to deal with so potent an Enemy they began to consult, to whose Protection they had best to betake themselves; and first they declare by their writings directed to all people, that <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> was fallen from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and therewith imposed an oath upon the People never to return again to the <hi>Spanish</hi> Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. This done, they Elected <hi>Francis</hi> Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> Heir Apparent to the <hi>French</hi> Crown, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99816:5"/>then in great hopes of Marrying <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Queen of <hi>England,</hi> to be their Lord, who being setled in his Government, and made at <hi>Antwerp</hi> Duke of <hi>Brabant, Limburg,</hi> and <hi>Lorreine,</hi> he presently gave free leave for the Exercise of the Romish Religion, to as many as would swear fealty to him, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Authority, intending ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to settle a Tyranny in himself, then to drive it from the <hi>Spaniard;</hi> and to this purpose, to strengthen himself, he attempts the strong City of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> put his Men into the Town, but it was by the Valour of the <hi>Burgers</hi> shamefully repulsed; the shame of this Ignoble Enterprize, together with some other disgraces, took such an impression upon him, as soon after he died with grief. At that time was the State of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> by the invention of some quick wits,
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> of <hi>Belgium.</hi>
               </note> thus described in this Hyrogli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick; a Cow represented the body of <hi>Belgium,</hi> there stood the King of <hi>Spain</hi> kicking her, the Queen of <hi>England</hi> feeding her, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> milking her, and the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> plucking her by the tayle, but she bewrayed his fingers.</p>
            <p>During the unfortunate Government of this Duke, the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> prevailed mightily, being victorious in all places where he came, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after the Death of <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who was treacherously slain by a shot of a Pistol; So that now the State of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> was truly miserable, having none to Lead them, none to Protect them, and desperate of pardon from their own Prince: Tryal they had made of other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99816:6"/>but found them to mind their own profit, more then theirs. <hi>England</hi> was now the only San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary they had left to fly unto, to the Queen whereof they humbly sue for Ayd and Protection, proffering her the Soveraignty of their Provinces, and earnestly beseeching her to receive into her Patronage, the poor distressed States. Great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate was in the Council about it, whether it was meet to receive them into Protection or no;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Martin</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued.</note> some were very much against it, accounting them no better then Disloyal to their Lawful Soveraign, and therefore unworthy of Assistance, besides the ill president to succeeding Princes, to countenance Disloyalty, though under never so specious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. Others were of a countrary opinion, that it was good to Receive and Aid them, least the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi> first conquering them, might with the more case annoy <hi>England;</hi> Besides, it was alleadged the Title that the Queen had to the Soveraignty of those Provinces, as being generally descended from <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, and <hi>Philip</hi> his Wife, who was Sister, and (as some report) Heir to <hi>William</hi> Earle of <hi>Hainaull, Holland &amp;c.</hi> Then if <hi>Margaret</hi> from whom the right of <hi>Spain</hi> is derived, were the Daughter of Earle <hi>William,</hi> then was our Queen to succeed after <hi>Philip</hi> who was rejected: if that <hi>Margaret</hi> were (as many report) his younger Sister, then was our Queen the undoubted-Heir; her predecessors <hi>Phillippa</hi> being Earle <hi>Williams</hi> Eldest Sister, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99816:6"/>
            <p>These things the Queen heard with great pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but refused at first to take them into prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, much less to exercise Soveraignty over them. But having intelligence that the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> had taken the strong Town of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded still on with admirable success: she look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the eyes of pity on the distressed State of these poor <hi>Netherlands,</hi> who were now as it were, expiring, and giving up the Ghost; she at last condescended to take them into protection: in doing which, as the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> said, she did as it were, <hi>take the Crown from her head, and lay it to stake on the doubtful chance of War,</hi> the whole World standing amazed at her valour, that by this Act durst as it were proclaim open. War against the most potent Monarch in <hi>Europe,</hi> in which she must of necessity expend a world of wealth,
<note place="margin">Martin.</note> besides the loss of many a gallant <hi>English man,</hi> and all this for an unthankful Nation, who were no sooner warm but they shewed their sting, and proved the onely great vexation (because deceitful friends) to that excellent Lady, who in those Infant days was both Mother and Nurse of their ungrateful Republick.</p>
            <p>Now the conditions of the League betwixt the Queen and the States, were these, <hi>The Queen shall send to the united Provinces a supply of five thousand Foot and a thousand Horse under a sufficient General, one of quality and experience, and shall pay them during the War: which money the States when there is a peace shall pay back again: namely, the first year of the Peace, the expences of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99816:7"/>the first years War, and the residue within four years after. The mean time the Queen shall have in Caution or Pledge delivered up</hi> Flushing, <hi>the Fort of</hi> Ramekins, <hi>and the Town of</hi> Briell, <hi>with the two Neighbouring Forts. The Governours of those places shall exercise no Rule over the Inhabitants, but the Garrison Souldiers onely, who shall pay all manner of Taxes and Impositions as well as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants. Those places upon payment of the money shall be given up to the States, and not to the King of</hi> Spain, <hi>or any other Enemie. The Governour and two other Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, whom the Queen shall nominate, shall be entertained into the States Privy Council. The States shall make no League or Confederacy without the Queens privity: nor she, but the States shall be made first acquainted,</hi> &amp;c. This agreement as it was very acceptable to all the <hi>Netherlanders,</hi> so in most especial manner to those of <hi>Zeland,</hi> who were so overjoyed thereat, that to continue the memory thereof to all posterity, they coined money with the figure of a Lyon recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself out of the Floods, and this Inscription on the one side, <hi>Luctor &amp; Emergo;</hi> and on the other this, <hi>Authore Deo, favente Regina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In prosecution of this agreement, soon after were those Cautionary Towns delivered unto the <hi>English.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir <hi>R Baker</hi>
               </note> Over <hi>Flushing</hi> and the Castle of <hi>Ramekins,</hi> was that deservedly honoured Gentleman, Sir <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Sidney</hi> made Governour. Not long after were great Forces sent over under the Command of the Earl of <hi>Leicester,</hi> who went thither in great pomp and glory, accompanied with the Earl of <hi>Essex,</hi> the Lords <hi>Audley</hi> and <hi>North,</hi> Sir <hi>William Russell,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99816:7"/>Sir <hi>Thomas Shirley,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Basset,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> Sir <hi>Gervas Clifton,</hi> and other renowned Knights, besides five hundred Gentlemen, many of whom spent their dearest lives in defence of those people, whose great unworthiness hath since demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated to the World how unworthily they have deserved such bloud to be spilt, without whom they could not have subsisted.</p>
            <p>But before we proceed any further in these Wars, it will not be amiss to shew the Noble dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position and candour of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that what she did was not out of ambition, nor avaritious ends, but onely meer pity and commiseration of the distressed condition of those miserable people. For having had knowledge how the States-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral had by Patent committed to the Earl of <hi>Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> the high Command and absolute Authority o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the United Provinces, with the Titles of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, and Captain General of <hi>Holland, Zeland,</hi> and the Confederate Provinces, and how he was guarded with a great Retinue, and saluted by all persons with the Title of his <hi>Excellency;</hi> she forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to signifie her displeasure thereof, sent Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the States-General, wherein she thus expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stulateth: <hi>That to her great disparagement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Martins</hi> Contin.</note>
               <hi>they had cast upon the Earl of</hi> Leicester <hi>her Subject, the absolute Command over the United Provinces without her privity, when as she her self had utterly denyed it; and by her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration had given the whole Christian World to know that she affected no Dominion or Soveraignty in the Low-Countries, but onely lent her aid to poor distressed persons.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:99816:8"/>And therefore willed them <hi>to divest the Earl of</hi> Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester <hi>of that absolute Authority, whose bounds she had set him: not because she took not their Cause to heart, which by all means she would maintain, but onely to make provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for her. Honour, which she esteemed more precious then her life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return the <hi>English</hi> being there, loved not to lye idle, but performed many gallant Services worthy their Name and Nation; particularly that Honour of Chivalry, gallant Sir <hi>Phillip Sidney,</hi> who upon a sudden onset, took in the strong Town of <hi>Axel</hi> in <hi>Flanders;</hi> but in the full Curreir of his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, encountring with a party of the Enemies near <hi>Zutphen,</hi> he was unfortunately shot in the thigh, and five and twenty days after died in the flower of his Age, whose death caused a general lamentation amongst all sorts of people: he being a Gentleman in whom were comprised all Vertues and Valours that could be expected to recide in man. His Funerals were afterwards solemnized in sumptuous manner at S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church in <hi>London.</hi> Both Universities made Funeral Verses upon him, and <hi>New Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford</hi> framed an elegant Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie to his Honour. <hi>James</hi> King of <hi>Scotland</hi> made his Epitaph, which is yet preserved in a Table in the Cathedral Church of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> containing these Verses:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Weavers</hi> Funeral Monument.</note>England, Netherland, <hi>the Heavens and the Arts,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All Souldiers and the World, have made six parts</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99816:8"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of the Noble</hi> Sidney, <hi>for none will suppose</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That a small heap of stones can</hi> Sidney <hi>enclose.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>England <hi>hath his Body, for she it bred,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Netherland <hi>his Bloud, in her defence shed;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Heavens his Soul, the Arts his Fame,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All Souldiers the grief, the World his good Name.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithstanding the loss of this and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gallant men, with divers notable Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments performed by the <hi>English,</hi> yet the <hi>Dutchmen</hi> were of such lavish tongues, that they ceased not to rail on their Defenders with many reviling and opprobrious speeches; and at last so far prevailed with Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> that <hi>Leicester</hi> was called home; who at his departure gave some pieces of Gold to several of his friends, upon one side whereof was his own picture, on the other, a few wandring Sheep, and a Dog leaving them, but looking back: by the Dog these words, <hi>Invitus desero;</hi> by the Sheep these, <hi>Non gregem, sedingratos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The States General in the room of the Earl of <hi>Leicester</hi> chose <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Nassaw,</hi> son to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> by <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Saxany,</hi> daughter to <hi>Maurice</hi> the brave Elector; and over the <hi>English</hi> Forces by the Queens appointment was <hi>Peregrine</hi> Lord <hi>Willoughby</hi> made General. In this state stood the Affairs of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> at such time when as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> with their Invincible Armado (as they termed it) sought to devour all <hi>England</hi> at one mouthful.</p>
            <p>And now her own danger being over by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> yet was she as solicitous
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99816:9"/>to provide for the good and welfare of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands.</hi> At that time the <hi>Zelanders</hi> were at such difference with the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> that without their knowledge they craved protection of the <hi>French</hi> King, which being by him intimated to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> she was sore displeased thereat, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver left till she had made them good friends. Nay when as <hi>Groining</hi> a wealthy Town of <hi>Friezland,</hi> which could not endure the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Command, nor would not submit to the States, sued to her for Protections she refused to receive it, so kind was she, and ready to do all good Offices to that Nation, who have since ill requited the <hi>English</hi> for their pains.</p>
            <p>Ten years had now the War endured, in which time, what a deal of <hi>English</hi> bloud was spilt in their quarrel! and the whole Land thereby greatly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hausted both of money and Military men, with the long continued War against the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who for no other cause became our Enemie, but for assisting them in their greatest necessity: so that now they are secured, and their Dominions enlarged by the <hi>English</hi> means, insomuch that they were able to lend aid to their Neighbours. Nay they were grown so high upon the aid of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish,</hi> that when certain Delegates met at <hi>Bulloign</hi> about a Peace betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> they were so far from regarding a Peace, that at the same time they had a thought of reducing the Sea Coast of <hi>Flanders</hi> under their Command. To which purpose they landed an Army there of 14000 Foot
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99816:9"/>and 3000 Horse, under the Command of <hi>Maurice</hi> on <hi>Nassaw;</hi> and 1500 of <hi>English</hi> under the Conduct of Sir <hi>Francis Vere,</hi> and his Brother <hi>Horatio.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir <hi>R Baker</hi>
               </note> At which time chanced the famous Battel of <hi>Newport</hi> against the Archduke and the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> wherein fell 9000 of the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> which Victory was chiefly obtained by the incomparable Valour and, Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity of the <hi>English,</hi> as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> themselves confessed though it cost them dear, 800 of their 1500 being slain and sore wounded.</p>
            <p>Thus we see through the series of this discourse how candidly the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> dealt with the <hi>Netherlanders,</hi> being so far off from self ends in the business, that she refused all advantages which might in the least seem derogatory to her honour. And whereas it is the nature of most Princes to make up their own ends upon other Nations mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series, she was so contrary from taking advantage of their calamities (although she had a golden opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity put into her hands) that by the aiding of them, she not onely exhausted her Treasure, lost many brave Heroick persons in their quarrel, but also engaged the most potent Monarch in Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be her Enemy. Now who could think such stupendious curtesies could be so soon buried in the Grave of Oblivion; or that a Nation could be so unworthy as to play the Snake in the Fable, seek to destroy those who had preserved them; or to injure that Nation who themselves had not been a People without their aid. And yet such we find them to be, for by the <hi>English</hi> aid being now grown
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99816:10"/>potent not onely at home, but also in Forreign Countries, they began to grow insolent even in the very time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who had been their Protector and Defendress. After her death, King <hi>James</hi> coming to the Crown, who was a Prince of a peaceable inclination, they grew higher and higher, offering many affronts to the <hi>English,</hi> especially in the <hi>East-Indies,</hi> where now they had arrived to a great height of Trade; insomuch that several complaints came to the King and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil against their proceedings; which occasioned two several Treaties,
<note place="margin">Jo. Selden. Mare Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum.</note> the one at <hi>London Anno</hi> 1613. the other at the <hi>Hague</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> in the year 1615. which by their cunning evasions proved to be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less. At last in a third Treaty, <hi>Anno</hi> 1619. there was a full and solemn Composition made of all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences betwixt them, and a fair Order set for their future proceedings. Amongst other Articles, one was, that these Islands which were then in possession of the <hi>English</hi> should continue theirs, of which <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laraon,</hi> one of the Islands of <hi>Banda</hi> was one. But notwithstanding this Agreement, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the publishing thereof in the <hi>Indies</hi> until such time they had taken the said Island of <hi>Palaroon,</hi> and that upon a very slight occasion, as you shall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand. A young man an <hi>Orankeys</hi> son, a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Palaroon</hi> had committed Fellony, for which he was to suffer death by the Laws of that Country; but he to save his life, fled to another Island called <hi>Landa,</hi> and there turned Christian: but understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that would not keep him from punishment,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99816:10"/>he afterwards went to another Island called <hi>Nera,</hi> where the <hi>Dutch</hi> had a strong Fort, and there infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the <hi>Netherlandlish</hi> Governour, that the <hi>Oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keys</hi> of <hi>Palaroon</hi> had conspired to destroy the <hi>Dutch</hi> as well at <hi>Pallaroon</hi> as at <hi>Poloney</hi> by the assistance of the people of <hi>Seran,</hi> who should send over thirty Curricurries for that intent. Upon this Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, certain Fisher-boats of the <hi>Palaroons</hi> that were fishing at <hi>Poloney,</hi> were seized upon, and the men committed to prison.
<note place="margin">Hist. of <hi>Amboyna.</hi>
               </note> Then did they send to <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roon</hi> for the rest of the <hi>Orankeys</hi> to appear before them; and they being innocent, not dreading any danger, as intending none, to the number of 70 with their Priest appeared before them; who were all immediately committed to Prison: afterwards with a force of two hundred men, they entered <hi>Palaroon,</hi> and brought all the rest of the <hi>Orankeys</hi> Prisoners to their Castle; and having by tortures forced Confessions from them, a hundred sixty and two of them, together with their Priest were condemned and executed: their Wives, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and Slaves, being distributed into other Islands subject to the <hi>Dutch</hi> Command. Then did they demolish and deface the buildings, transplant the Nutmeg Trees, plucking them up by the roots, and planting them in other Islands of their own, by this means making the Island of little use or profit to the <hi>English,</hi> as destitute of Trees, and especially people, without whom neither the <hi>English</hi> nor the <hi>Hollanders</hi> can maintain their Trade in the <hi>Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99816:11"/>
            <p>Soon after, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>March</hi> 1623. they proceeded to Acts of a more higher nature, so great and blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that were it not confirmed by infallible Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, Posterity might seem to doubt that any People professing Christianity, should upon such slight surmised accounts, commit the same: the manner whereof we shall briefly deliver unto you.</p>
            <p>Among other Islands in the <hi>East Indies</hi> wherein the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> traded; <hi>Amboyna</hi> was one; wherein (according to the agreement made at the Treaty in <hi>London, Anno</hi> 1619.) the <hi>Hollanders</hi> (for some charges they pretended to be at in winning of the Trade of those Parts from the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Portugals</hi>) were to enjoy two third parts of the Trade; and the <hi>English</hi> the other. In pursuance of which Agreement, the English <hi>East India</hi> Merchants had planted certain Factories there, of which at that present Captain <hi>Gabriel Towerson</hi> was Master.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> exceeded very much in number, and for their defence had built there a very strong For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tress, with four Points or Bulwarks, and upon each of them Points six great pieces of Ordnance mounted, most of them of Brass. This Fort was defended by 200 <hi>Dutch</hi> Souldiers, and a Company of Free Burgers, besides some three or four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Mardikers</hi> (as they called the Natives) ready to serve them at an hours warning. Here did these two Nations keep Trading together for about two years, though not without some difference and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99816:11"/>jarrs; the <hi>English</hi> complaining that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> lavished away much money in building, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary expences upon the Forts, and the like, by that means bringing large and unreasonable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts to the common reckoning, so contriving the Common Actions and Charge to their private advantage. But these were but petty injuries in respect of that which was acted soon after, and which we now come to relate.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Japoner</hi> Souldier of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> walking one night upon the Wall of the Castle of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> grew so inquisitive as to ask the Centinel (a <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>) some questions concerning the strength of the Castle, and the number of people therein; for which he was apprehended and put to the torture: so dangerous a thing it is to meddle with Edge Tools, or to seek to be wise in that whose know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge may do us hurt. This <hi>Japoner</hi> through the extremity of pain, was brought to confess that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self and sundry others of his Country men had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived to surprize the Castle; which occasioned divers others of them to be examined and tortured, and at last drew out a confession from them, that the <hi>English</hi> were concerned with them therein. Hereupon one <hi>Abel Price</hi> Chirurgeon of the <hi>English</hi> (who was then a Prisoner in the Castle, for offering in his drunkenness to have set a <hi>Dutch mans</hi> house on fire) was by them brought to the torture, which he being not able to endure, soon confessed what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever they would have him. Upon his confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they presently sent for Captain <hi>Towerson,</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99816:12"/>the rest of the <hi>English,</hi> who lived not in the Castle, but under Protection thereof, in a house of their own in the Town; who appearing before the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, he told them that they were accused of a Conspiracy to surplize the Castle and therefore till further Trial they were to remain Prisoners. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus secured the men, they send to search the house, where all the Military provision they found was onely three Swords, two Hand-guns, and about half a pound of Powder. Great provisions sure to effect such things as were laid to their charge! How ever they would not, or at least would not seem to be convinced of their innocency, but immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately sent to the two other Factories in the same Island; apprehending the rest of the <hi>English</hi> there: as also at <hi>Cambello</hi> and <hi>Loho,</hi> and brought them in irons unto <hi>Amboyna.</hi> The names of all which Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners were as followeth: Captain <hi>Gabriel Towerson, Abel Price,</hi> who was a Prisoner before, <hi>Emanuel Thom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pson, John Beamont, Edward Collins, William Webber, Ephraim Ramsey, Timothy Johnson, John Fardo, Robert Brown, Samuel Colson, John Clark, George Sharrock, John Sadler, John Powl, John Wetheral, Thomas Ladbrook,</hi> and <hi>William Grigs.</hi> Having them thus in Custody, they proceed by tortures to make them confess whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was asked them. The manner of which Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we shall for the rarity thereof deliver it unto you; First they hoised them up by the hands with a Cord upon a large Door, making them fast with two Staples of iron, fixt on both sides at the top of the Door posts, so halling their hands one from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99816:12"/>the other as wide as ever they could make them to stretch: having thus fastned their hands, and their body hoised some two Foot from the ground, then they stretcht their legs asunder as far as they would reach, which they likewise made fast beneath unto the Door posts, on each side. Next they bound a cloth about their neck and face, so close as that little or no water could go by: this done, they poured the water softly upon their heads till the cloth was full up to the mouth and nostrils, or somewhat higher; insomuch that in drawing their breath they must of necessity suck in the water, which with long continuance, forced all their inward parts, coming out of their nose, ears, and eyes, so stifling and choaking them, that at last it took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their breath, and brought them into a swou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning condition; then would they take them down and make them vomit up their water again, and being a little recovered, hoice them up again, and serve them as before. Thus would they handle them three or four several times together, till their bodies would be swollen sometimes twice or thrice as big as before, their Cheeks shewing like to great blown bladders, and their Eyes staring and struting out beyond their foreheads. And now if they would not confess whatsoever they would have them to do, then would they torment them by a contrary Element, setting burning Candles to the bottomes of their feet whilest they were thus hanging, continuing so till many times the fat dropt out the Candles, and they were forced to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99816:13"/>fresh lights. They would also burn them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the elbows, in the palms of their hands, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their arm-pits, till their very inwards might evidently be seen. Thus did they serve severall of the <hi>English,</hi> forcing them by these mercilesse tortures, to confesse and say whatsoever they would have them, and to accuse both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves and others of crimes they never had ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined.</p>
            <p>And now at last from torturing they came to Condemnation, and soon after proceeded to Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, twenty persons dying for this surmized of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, <hi>viz.</hi> ten <hi>English,</hi> nine <hi>Japoneses,</hi> and a <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> the Guardian of the Slaves under the <hi>Dutch.</hi> The names of the <hi>English</hi> are as followeth; Captain <hi>Gabriel Towerson,</hi> the Agent of the <hi>English</hi> at <hi>Amboy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na; Samuel Colson,</hi> Factor at <hi>Hitto; Emanuel Tomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> Assistant at <hi>Amboyna; Timothy Johnson,</hi> Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant there also; <hi>John Wetheral,</hi> Factor at <hi>Cambello; John Clark,</hi> Assistant at <hi>Hitto; William Griggs,</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor at <hi>Larica; John Fardo,</hi> Steward of the House; <hi>Abel Price,</hi> Chirurgian; and <hi>Robert Brown,</hi> Talor.</p>
            <p>The name of the <hi>Portugal</hi> that suffered with them was <hi>Augustine Perez,</hi> born at <hi>Bengala.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To satisfie the Inquisitive, here also follows the names of those <hi>Japoneses</hi> that suffered with them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hititso</hi> born at <hi>Firando.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tsiosa</hi> born at <hi>Firando.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sinsa</hi> born at <hi>Firando.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:99816:13"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sidney Migiel</hi> born at <hi>Nagansarque.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pedro Congie</hi> born at <hi>Nagansarque.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thome Coreu</hi> born at <hi>Nagansarque.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quiandayo,</hi> Native of <hi>Corvets.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tsabinda</hi> of <hi>Ttsoncketgo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Zanchoe</hi> of <hi>Fisien.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Dutch in their examinations were so poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickly cruel; as to make both the <hi>English</hi> and the <hi>Japoners</hi> believe that each had accused other: which made the <hi>Japoners</hi> to cry out upon the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish,</hi> saying, <hi>Oh you</hi> English <hi>men! where did we ever in our lives eat with you, talk with you, or (to our best re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance) ever see you?</hi> To which the <hi>English</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, <hi>Why then did you accuse us?</hi> Whereupon they perceiving how deceitfully they had been used, shewed them their tortured bodies, saying, <hi>If a stone were thus burnt, would it not change its Nature? how much more we that are but flesh and bloud!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the <hi>Dutch</hi> cruelty we may add their avari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciousness: for having prepared a Cloth of black Velvet for Captain <hi>Towersons</hi> body to fall upon, and it being thereby somewhat stained and defaced with his bloud, they afterwards put it upon the <hi>English</hi> Companies account.</p>
            <p>Now though to any discerning Reader, the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of these men may sufficiently appear, yet for further satisfaction, we shall give you an account of some other things which happened at that time, and were by understanding persons interpreted as a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99816:14"/>token of the wrath of God for this barbarous tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Hollanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the very instant of the Execution, there arose such a horrible darkness, together with a sudden and Violent Tempest and Gust of Winde; that two of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships then riding in the Harbour, were by the violence thereof driven from their Anchors, and were not without much difficulty preserved from the Rocks. Some few days after one <hi>William Dunckin</hi> who had informed the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that <hi>Robert Brown</hi> the <hi>English</hi> Taylor had told him some few Moneths before, that he hoped e're six Moneths were ended, the <hi>English</hi> should have as much to do in the Castle of <hi>Amboyna</hi> as the <hi>Dutch.</hi> This man coming to the Grave one Evening, where the <hi>English</hi> (all but Captain <hi>Towerson</hi>) were buried in a Pit, he suddenly fell down thereupon, and having lien there some while, rose again di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted of his Wits; and so continuing two or three days together in that ravening posture, he thon died. At the heels of this, fell a new and unwonted sickness amongst them, which swept away about a thousand people <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Amboyners,</hi> in that space wherein commonly there died not above thirty or forty persons at other sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</p>
            <p>But part of their revenge was reserved for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther season,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hamm. L'Strange.</hi> History of King <hi>Charls</hi> the First.</note>
               <hi>viz.</hi> the year 1630. seven years after this horrible cruelty; which according as I find it delivered in an Author of good account, I shall impart it to you in his own Words.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99816:14"/>
            <p>Eighteen <hi>Hollanders</hi> (whereof three had been Actors in the <hi>English</hi> Tragedy at <hi>Amboynd</hi>) supping at <hi>Francksort</hi> (a City in Germany) as they were passing to <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> boasted in their cups what they had done to our Nation in that Island, which one in their Company observing, related it to two <hi>English</hi> Captains of Horse then in service of the Emperours, and two of whose kindred suffered there. These two Captains having notice which way the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were to pass way-laid them in a Wood with a Troop of Horse; and having met them, bad them stand: that done, willed them to prepare for death, for die they must. The <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> replied, <hi>they hoped not so, for all their mony was at their dispose.</hi> We seek not your money, said the two Captains, but your lives, and will now be revenged for those barbarous torments three of this your Company put our Country men and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to at <hi>Amboyna:</hi> and had we leisure we would serve you so too. First, they hung up <hi>Johnson</hi> the chief of the <hi>Amboynests,</hi> and made the other seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen cast the Dice which of them should escape to carry the Intelligence into <hi>Holland.</hi> The fifteen guiltless persons thought this hard measure, and hoped they would not punish them for others faults. But the Gentlemen pleaded, <hi>Legem talio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> and that they might as well hang them, as their Countrymen were butchered at <hi>Amboyna</hi> without cause. So without further Indictment they hang'd up sixteen, and sent the odd man home. Some sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, but, although almost two for one, not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99816:15"/>equiparate to the merrit of that Nations cruelty: These seventeen had a mercifull and quick dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch; our ten at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> the ingenious Devills did so exquisitely torture, as the poor Patients had nothing but clear consciences, to make them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they felt not Hell above ground.</p>
            <p>But to return, he that throughly considers this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness in all the parts thereof, and with what impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities there could be of a Plot, or what ground there could be for any such conceits as was pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; certainly, he that considers all things, must needs conclude it to be a mad Plot, for which Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Towerson</hi> might rather have been sent to <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam,</hi> or the <hi>Dullen-hoff</hi> (as the <hi>Dutch</hi> term it) then to the Gallows.</p>
            <p>For with what confidence durst ten English men (whereof scarce one of them a Souldier) attempt any thing upon such a defensible place, and how ill provided were they for it? there being (as we said before) found at the Seizure of their house, onely three Swords, two Muskets, and about half a pound of Powder; terrible Provision to perform wonders, and which might sute well for a Romance, not a Reality: As for the assistance of the <hi>Japons,</hi> they were but ten neither, and all unarmed as well as the <hi>English;</hi> neither was there any Ship or Pinnace of the <hi>English</hi> in the Harbour at that time; whereas the <hi>Hollanders</hi> had then in the Road Eight Ships, and Vessells of good defence and burthen. It is true indeed, our Chronicles do report many gallant he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick actions performed by the <hi>English,</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99816:15"/>can witness divers of them; yea, oftentimes hath reaped the fruit of the <hi>English</hi> Resolution: but scarce any Story or Legend do report such fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hardiness, either of the <hi>English</hi> or others, that so inconsiderate a party, destitute of all provisions and supp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc></desc>
               </gap>ies, should dare to undertake such an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture upon a counter-party so extraordinarily provided in all points.</p>
            <p>But should we particularize all the injuries and contumelies by the <hi>Dutch</hi> done to the <hi>English,</hi> they would make our Book swell to too great a Vollum; we shall therefore only summarily run over some most material,
<note place="margin">Hist. Ambol.</note> leaving the rest to more Vollumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Historians: And first, in their Invasion of the Islands of <hi>Lantore</hi> and <hi>Polaroone,</hi> which they forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly wrested from the <hi>English,</hi> raised and demolished their Forts, binding the <hi>English</hi> (though not so much as resisted by them) to Stakes, with Ropes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their necks, almost strangling them with the same, then flourishing their naked Swords about them, as if they would presently dispatch them out of the World; and being thus amazed and bound, tumble them down the Rocks, and after carry their crushed and brused bodies away in Irons.</p>
            <p>In other places did they pretend to such a height of Jurisdiction, that they would take upon them the conusance of controversies between the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Indians,</hi> and though beyond the compass of their bounds yet would they presume to pass sentence, and execute the same by plain force, by seizing of the <hi>English</hi> Companies goods, Fining, Imprisoning,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99816:16"/>Stocking, yea, Whipping our People at a Post in the Market-place, and then washing them with vinegar and salt.</p>
            <p>To these we might add injuries in point of part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nership, as their putting great summs to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Account,
<note place="margin">J. Seldens</note> which were disbursed to the private gain and behoofe of the <hi>Dutch;</hi> giving great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents for the glory of their Nation, without (nay against) the consent of the <hi>English;</hi> and making War for the inlargement of their own Dominion, yet bringing the charge to the Common Account; with infinite other the like particulars, too long here to recite; all which, with many other indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of the like nature, we may ascribe to their insatiable covetousnesse, to gain thereby the sole trade of the <hi>Mollucco's, Banda,</hi> and <hi>Aboyna,</hi> which was the main end of their designs.</p>
            <p>But to look alittle back, in matters betwixt the two Nations nearer home; where we shall find them as busie to encroach upon the <hi>English</hi> Rights, and to gain that which God and Nature hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed upon us. <hi>viz.</hi> the Fishing in our narrow Seas, thereby eating the bread out of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand <hi>English</hi> Mens mouths, contrary to their right, His Majesty of Great <hi>Brittain</hi> having the sole Power and Command of Fishing upon all the Coasts of his three Kingdomes as hath been asserted by divers Learned Authors; Yet so bold were they therein even as it were, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign that he was forced to assert his right by Proclaimation, wherein he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99816:16"/>all persons the use of the Seas upon our Coasts, without particular License, part of which Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation containing the grounds thereof, take as follows.</p>
            <p>Whereas we have been contented since our coming to the Crown,
<note place="margin">J. Selden. Contin.</note> to tollerate an indifferent and promiscuous kind of liberty to all our friends whatsoever, to fish within our streams, and upon any of our Coasts of Great <hi>Brittain, Ireland,</hi> and other adjacent Islands, so far forth as the permission or use thereof might not redound to the impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Prerogative Royal, nor to the hurt and damage of our loving subject, whose preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and flourishing estate we hold our self Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally bound to advance before all worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects: So finding that our continuance therein, hath not only given occasion of over-great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments upon our Regalities, or rather Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stioning for our right, but hath been a means of daily wrongs to our own people that exercise the trade of fishing, as (either by the multitude of strangers, which do preoccupie those places, or by the injuries which they receive most commonly at their hands our Subjects are constrained to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don their fishing, or at least are become so discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged in the same, as they hold it better for them to betake themselves to some other course of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, whereby not only divers of our Coast-towns are much decayed, but the number of Marriners daily diminished, which is a matter of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence to our Estate, considering how much the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99816:17"/>strength thereof consisteth in the Power of Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and use of Navigation; We have thought it now both just and necessary in respect that we are now by Gods favour Lineally and Lawfully possessed, as well of the Island of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> as of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the rest of the Isles adjacent to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think our selves of good lawfull means to prevent those inconveniences, and many others depending upon the same. In consideration whereof, as we are desirous that the World may take notice, that we have no intention to deny our Neighbours, and Allies, those Fruits and Benefits of peace and friendship, which may be justly expected at our hands in Honour and Reason, or are afforded by other Princes mutually in the point of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and exchange of those things which may not prove prejudicial to them: So because some such convenient order may be taken in this matter as may sufficiently provide for all those important considerations which do depend thereupon; We have resolved first to give notice to all the World, that our express pleasure is, That from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Month of <hi>August</hi> next coming, no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of what Nation or Quality soever, being not our Natural born Subjects, be permitted to fish up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any of our Coasts, and Seas of Great <hi>Brittain, Ireland,</hi> and the rest of the Isles ad acent, where most usually heretofore any fishing hath been, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they have orderly demanded and obtained Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censes from us, or such our Commissioners, as we have Authorized in that behalf, <hi>viz.</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99816:17"/>our Realms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and at <hi>Edenbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough</hi> for our Realm of <hi>Scotland;</hi> which Licenses, our intention is, shall be yearly demanded, for so many Vessels and Ships, and the Tonnage thereof, as shall intend to fish for that whole year, or any part thereof, upon any of our Coasts and Seas as aforesaid, upon pain of such chastisement, as shall be fit to be inflicted upon such wilfull offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>But notwithstanding this Proclamation, and the Kings care for the good of his Subjects, the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlanders</hi> ceased not still to use their old way of encroachment upon our Seas and Coasts, during the time that King <hi>James</hi> Reigned; and grew at length so bold, as to contest with him for the same, and to that purpose hired <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> (a man of great Learning, and Extraordinary Knowledge, in things both Divine and Humane) to assert and maintain a natural and perpetual Community of the Sea; which he handled in two Books; The one called, <hi>Mare Liberum,</hi> the other, <hi>De Jure Belli &amp; Pacis;</hi> which opinion intrenching upon the King of <hi>Englands</hi> Right and Prerogative; Sir <hi>Dudley Carleton,</hi> then Lord Ambassadour there, desired might be supprest, and the Authour punisht, <hi>That others by his Example might be deterred from defending that Opinion.</hi> These works of <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards Answered, and his Majesties Right and Prerogative maintained, by the Pen of the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Selden,</hi> in a Book called, <hi>Mare Clausum,</hi> which is now Extant.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99816:18"/>
            <p>But though King <hi>James</hi> was minded stithy to maintain his Dominion over the Seas, (a Right which his Progenitors had possessed invioably for many hundreds of years) yet were they so bold as to endeavour to quarrel him out of his Right, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending a Right of their own by <hi>Immemorial Posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> because of the long connivance of Himself; and Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and this, some of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners which were sent over hither, had the confidence to plead in <hi>Terminis</hi> to the King and his Council. And notwithstanding the King did oft insist upon his Right, not onely by his Council to their Commissioners, and by his Ambassadour to their Superiours, yet did his indulgence gain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from them, but artificial Delaies, Pretences Shifts, Dilatory Addresses, and Evasive Answers; and in conclusion,
<note place="margin">Sir. <hi>R Baker</hi>
               </note> onely a verbal acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of those Rights, which at the same time that they acknowledged, they usually designed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade with much more insolence then formerly.</p>
            <p>In this presumptuous course did they continue the Reign of King <hi>James,</hi> as also the beginning of the Reign of his Son, our late dread Soveraign; Insomuch, that at length, they fell to a down-right Impeachment of his Right, not in words only, but by contemning the Command of his Officers, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting the <hi>English</hi> free Commerce within their own Seas; abusing and disturbing the Subjects at Sea, and the King himself in his very-Ports, and Chambers; and by many other actions of so intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable a nature, that in the Year, 1635. He gave
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99816:18"/>Order for the setting forth of a Powerfull Fleet, to check the Audacious Designes and Attempts of those unthankfull Neighbours; and in prosecution of his purpose, sent forth a Proclamation for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint of Fishing on the Seas and Coasts without License, which Proclamation served to speak the mind and intent of those Naval preparations then inhand; which were so numerous and well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> themselves being touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an apprehension of their own Guiltiness, for their bold Encroachments, soon betrayed their jealousies and fears, and in them a sence of their offences, before ever the Proclamation was made Publique. But since the grounds and reasons of preparing that Gallant Navy, with the Kings Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to maintain his Right, derived to him from his Royal Ancestors, are contained at large, in an Acute Letter sent from one Secretary <hi>Cooke,</hi> to Sir <hi>William Boswell,</hi> the Kings Resident then at the <hi>Hague.</hi> I shall spare the pains of writing further, and deliver, it unto you in his words, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BY your Letters and otherwise, I perceive ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny jealousies and discourses are raised upon the preparations of his Majesties Fleet,
<note place="margin">J. Selden.</note> which is now in such forwardness, that we doubt not but within this Month it will appear at Sea. It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore expedient both for your Satisfaction and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, to Inform you particularly what was the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99816:19"/>occasion, and what is his Majesties intention in this work.</p>
                  <p>First, we hold it a Principle not to be denyed, that the King of Great <hi>Brittain</hi> is a Monarch at Land and Sea, to the full extent of his Dominions, and that it concerneth him as much to maintain his Soveraignty in all the <hi>Brittish</hi> Seas, as within his Three Kingdomes; Because, without that, these cannot be kept safe; nor he preserve his Honour and due Respect with other Nations. But Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the Seas, he may cause his Neighbours, and all Countries to stand upon their Guard when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever he thinks fit. And this cannot be doubted, that whosoever will Encroach upon him by Sea, will do it by Land also, when they see their time. To such presumption <hi>Mare Liberum</hi> gave the first Warning-piece, which must be Answered with a defence of <hi>Mare Clausum,</hi> not so much by Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, as by the louder Language of a Powerfull Navy, to be better understood, when over-strained patience seeth no hope of preserving her Right by other means.</p>
                  <p>The Degrees, by which his Majesties Dominion at Sea hath of late Years been first impeached, and then questioned, are as considerable as notorious.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>First,</hi> to cherish, and as it were, to nurse up our unthankfull Neighbours, we gave them leave to gather wealth and strength upon our Coasts, in our Ports, by our Trade, and by our People. Then they were glad to invite our Merchants Residence with what Privileges they would desire. Then
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99816:19"/>they offered to us the Soveraignty of their Estates, and then they sued for License to Fish upon the Coasts, and obtained it under the great Seal of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which now they suppress. And when thus by leave, or by connivance, they had possessed themselves of our Fishings, and onely in <hi>Scotland,</hi> but in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> not by our Staple had raised a great stock of Trade; by these means they so encreas'd their Shipping and Power at Sea, that now they endure not to be kept at any distance: Nay, they are grown to that confidence to keep Guards upon our Seas, and then to project an office and Company of Assurance for the Advancement of Trade; and withall, prohibet us free Commerce even within our own Seas, and take our Ships and Goods, if we conform not to their Placarts. What Insolencies and Cruelties they have committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us heretofore, in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in <hi>Greenland,</hi> and in the <hi>Indies,</hi> is too well known to all the World. In all which, though our sufferings and their wrong may seem forgotten, yet the greatest interest of his Majesties Honour, is still the same, and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fresh their memories as there shall be cause: For, though charity must reunite wrongs done to private men, yet the reflection upon the Publique, may make it a greater charity to do Justice on crying crimes. All this notwithstanding, you are not to conceive that the work of this Fleet, is either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, or execution of Justice for these great Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences past; but chiefly, for the future to stop the violent current of that presumption whereby the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99816:20"/>Men of War, and Free-booters of all Nations (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busing the Favour of his Majesties Peaceable and Gracious Government, whereby he hath permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all his Friends and Allies, to make use of his Seas and Ports in a reasonable and free manner, and according to his Treaties) have taken upon them the boldness, not onely to come confidently at all times into all his Ports and Rivers, but to conveigh their Merchants Ships as high as his Chief City, and then to cast Anchor close upon his Magazins, and to contemn the Commands of his Officers, when they required a further distance: But which is more intollerable, have Assaulted and Taken one another within his Majesties Chamber, and within his Rivers, to the same scorn and contempt of his Dominion and Power; and this being of late years an ordinary practice which we have endeavoured in vain to reform by the waies of Justice and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the World I think will now be satisfied, that we have reason to look about us. And no wise man will doubt that it is high time to put our selves in this Equipage upon the Seas, and not to suffer that Stage of action to be taken from us for want of our appearance.</p>
                  <p>So you see the general ground upon which our Counsels stand; In particular, you may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, and publish as cause requires; That his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty by this Fleet intendeth not a Rupture with any Prince or State, nor to infringe any point of his Treaties; but resolveth to continue and maintain that Happy Peace wherewith God hath blessed his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99816:20"/>Kingdome; and to which all his Actions and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations have hither tended, as by your own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions you may fully understand. But withall considering, that Peace must be maintained by the Arm of Power, which onely keeps down War, by keeping up Dominion, his Majesty thus provoked, finds it necessary even for his own Defence and Safety, to Re-assume and keep his Antient and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Right in the Dominion of these Seas, and to suffer no other Prince or State to Encroach upon Him, thereby assuming to Themselves or their Admiralls, any Soveraign Command; but to force them to perform due homage to his Admiralls and Ships, and to pay them acknowledgements, as in former times they did. He will also set open, and protect the Free Trade both of his Subjects and Allies: And give them such safe Conduct and Convoy, as they shall reasonably require. He will suffer no other Fleets or Men of War, to keep any Guard upon those Seas, or there to offer Violence, or take Prizes, or Booties, or to give Interruption to any lawfull intercourse. In a word, his Majesty is resolved, as to do no Wrong, so to do Justice both to his Subjects and Friends, within the limmits of his Seas. And this is the Real and Royal design of this Fleet, whereof you may give part as you find occasion to our good Neighbours in those parts, that no umbrage may be taken of any Hostile act or purpose to their prejudice in any kind: So wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you all health and happiness, I Rest</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your assured Friend and Servant</hi> Jo. Cook.</signed>
                     <dateline>Whitehall, <date>16. <hi>April,</hi> 1635. <hi>Old Stile.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:99816:21"/>
            <p>In this Letter you see first, how it was held for an undeniable Principle, that the King was King as well by Sea as by Land; That neither the Honour nor Safety of this Island and <hi>Ireland</hi> could be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, but by preserving the Dominion by Sea; and that it is an Argument, that they that Encroach upon us by Sea, will do it also by Land when they see their time. He declares also, how our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull Neighbours are risen, to this height and insolence, partly by grant, partly by connivance, but principally through their many injurious abuses of our Patience and Indulgence. And lastly, you may observe here what Resolutions were then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to prevent the like injuries, and preserve our <hi>English</hi> Interest in time to come; And no doubt, but that Prudent Prince would with his Navall Forces have brought down their insolency, had his Subjects been as forward to have supplyed Him in that necessary occasion, as they were afterwards to contribute to His Enemies against Him.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithstanding all hinderances, <hi>Anno</hi> 1635. The King set out a Gallant Fleet of Threescore Saile,
<note place="margin">Sir R. Baker</note> whereof the Earle of <hi>Lindsey</hi> was Admirall, and the Earle of <hi>Essex</hi> Vice-Admiral; who scow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Seas from Pirats formerly molesting, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our Commodities were safely transported, and the <hi>English</hi> Puissance rendred so considerable in the eyes of Forreign Princes, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> judged it his surest way to entrust his Bullion in our bottomes, which was Coyned in <hi>England,</hi> to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99816:21"/>benefit of the Kings Mint, as also to the Merchants, whose Commocities were exchanged thereby, the remainder of the Money being paid at <hi>Flanders</hi> by way of Exchange. At this time the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Hollanders</hi> had confederated together to infest the <hi>Spaniard</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> the one by Land, and the other by Sea; But the <hi>Hollanders</hi> are remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from before <hi>Dunkirk</hi> by the <hi>English</hi> Fleet, and the Natives discontented by the insolencies of the <hi>French;</hi> rose up in Armes against them, and joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> expelled them out of the Country.</p>
            <p>The good successe of this Fleet, Encouraged the King next Year to send another, consisting of the like number, under the Command of the Earle of <hi>Northumberland;</hi> who Sailing Northwards, scow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Seas of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Busses, seizing some, sink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others, and making the rest to fly; reducing them thereby to a precarious condition of entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the favour of Fishing by the Kings Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, and no doubt had not the disposition of his Affairs hindred him, he would have sufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained them from Encroaching upon his Rights in the Brittish Seas.</p>
            <p>But the Aversness of his Subjects to any comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Charge, was to him a great disadvantage, as on the other side, of great advantage to the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> who now were grown so presumptious as to set upon the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the <hi>Brittish</hi> Seas, which (as being both Friends to <hi>England</hi>) ought by Rule of State to have been an Harbour of Retreat to secure
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99816:22"/>the weaker from the Stronger, and not the Scene of their Hostile Engagement; the manner of which Fight we shall deliver unto you.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spanish</hi> Fleet consisting of near seventy Sail, under the Conduct of <hi>Don Antonio D'oquenda,</hi> with about Twenty Five Thousand Men,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hamm. L'Strange.</hi> History of King <hi>Charls</hi> the First.</note> and a consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able summe of Money, were Bound and Designed for a Recruit to <hi>Dunkirk</hi> in <hi>Flanders;</hi> but by the way, met with the <hi>Dutch</hi> Vice-Admiral, with se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen Sail of Good Men of War, by whom they were forced to an Engagement, which happened upon the 7th of <hi>September, Anno</hi> 1639. In which the <hi>Hollander</hi> perceiving himself too weak, got to the Wind-ward, Sailing along with them towards <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> continually firing their Ordnance upon them, to give warning to <hi>Van Trump</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, who lay before <hi>Dunkirk</hi> with the Residue of the Navy; In this Fight the <hi>Hollanders</hi> had two Ships sunk, but the next Morning by two of the Clock, the Admiral came up with ten Ships, and joyning Forces with the Vice-Admiral, between <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Calice,</hi> they fell upon the <hi>Spaniard</hi> in a very sharp Encounter, which continued the space of half a day, wherein the <hi>Dutch</hi> had much the better, taking two Gallions, sinking another, and sorely shattering the rest, though they were but Twenty Five Sail, to the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Sixty and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and at last forced them upon the <hi>English</hi> Coast near <hi>Dover,</hi> where they left them, and bore off towards <hi>France,</hi> till they might consult what was next to be done.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99816:22"/>
            <p>The beaten <hi>Spaniard,</hi> being now got as they thought under the Lee of <hi>Englands</hi> Protection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to divise how to get rid of their bad Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; and by their Resident importuned the King to Protect them from the <hi>Hollander</hi> for two Tides, that they might have convenience to get back again to <hi>Spain;</hi> But King <hi>Charles</hi> being in Amity with them both, would not meddle in the business, but was resolved to stand Neuter; And whereas the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had hired some <hi>English</hi> Ships to Transport their Souldiers to <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> the King understanding thereof, upon complaint of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ambassador, he forthwith gave strict Order, that none should take in any <hi>Spaniards,</hi> nor presume to passe beyond <hi>Gravesend</hi> without License: So both sides being let to themselves, Plotted a great while counter the one to the other; but the wily <hi>Spaniard</hi> at length somewhat out-witted his Enemy, and by a stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem in the Night conveyed away to <hi>Dunkirk</hi> Fourteen Ships, and in them Four Thousand Men, and Four Hundred Thousand Pounds in Silver. But the King unwilling to have them Engage in his Seas, in the beginning of <hi>October,</hi> sent the Earle of <hi>Arundel</hi> to <hi>Don Antonio</hi> D' <hi>oquenda</hi> the Admirall of <hi>Spain.</hi> to desire him to retreat the first fair Wind; but the Wind continuing contrary longer then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, detained them there so long, that the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> (who waited for his coming out) had daily fresh supply from <hi>Zealand,</hi> so that at length their Armado was compleated to an Hundred Ships: wherewith they encompassed their Enemies for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99816:23"/>some few dayes within Pistol shot of them; So that at the last this long Enterview betwixt these two great Navies turned to an Engagement.</p>
            <p>For on the 11th of the same Month, <hi>Van Trump</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Admirall, gave Command to his Fleet to fall on them, which they did with Cannon and Fireships in so furious a manner, as they unable to endure their shot, cut their Cables, and being Fifty Three in number, Twenty Three of them run on Shore, and stranded in the <hi>Downs,</hi> whereof three were burnt, two sunk, and two perished on the Shore; one of which was a great Gallion of Two and Fifty Brass Pieces of Ordnance, Commanded by the Vice Admiral of <hi>Gallizia, Don Andrew de Castro;</hi> the remainder of the Twenty Three were deserted by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who went to Land, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Ships to be Man'd by the <hi>English</hi> for safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guards from the <hi>Dutch.</hi> The other Thirty <hi>Spanish</hi> Ships under the Command of the Admiralls <hi>Don Antonio d'oquenda,</hi> and <hi>Lopus</hi> of <hi>Portugal,</hi> went to Sea, keeping in close order, till they were covered with a great Fogg, whereof the <hi>Dutch</hi> taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, interposed between the Admiralls and their Fleet and Fought them valiantly till the fogg cleared up, when the Admirall of <hi>Portugal</hi> began to flame, being Fired with two <hi>Holland</hi> Fire-ships, which <hi>D'oquenda</hi> perceiving, he presently took his course towards <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> with the poor remainder of his Ships, the most of the rest being lost and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; for of these Thirty, Eleven were sent Priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners into <hi>Holland,</hi> Three perished upon the Coast
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99816:23"/>of <hi>France;</hi> One near <hi>Dover,</hi> Five were sunk in the Fight, and onely Ten of them escaped.</p>
            <p>This daring of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to Fight thus on the Coast of <hi>England,</hi> was looked upon as an high affront to our King, and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> doubting that he would ill resent it, were willing to keep him so busied, that he should not have opportunity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and to that end, Commotions beginning to arise in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the <hi>Hollanders</hi> did not only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand Foment them, but also Accommodated them with all manner of Warlike Provision.</p>
            <p>What great Friends they were afterwards to the Long Parliament is sassiciently known, continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly supplying them with all necessaries to continue the breaches betwixt them and his Sacred Majesty; however, yet in the Year, 1640. there was some Overtures made by their Ambassadours to the King,
<note place="margin">Sir R. Baker Contin.</note> of a Match between <hi>William</hi> the Young Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the Princess <hi>Mary</hi> the Kings Eldest Laugnter; which Proposition was well li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of King <hi>Charles,</hi> who Communicated the same unto the Parliament, with whom it found a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and Unanimous Reception, in regard of the Alliance to be thereupon Concluded with the Prince his Father; as also, that the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces were of the same Protestant Religion with <hi>England,</hi> and so it was soon Concluded, and She Betrothed to Him, and after some little stay in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> went over into <hi>Holland</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc></desc>
               </gap>im accompanied with her Dear Mother, Popular Tumult being now grown so high, as rendred <hi>London</hi> no safe place for her person.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:99816:24"/>
            <p>But to pass over all those Unnatural Civil Wars in <hi>England,</hi> wherein the <hi>Hollanders</hi> made their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets by our Troubles; after the inhumane mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our late Dread Soveraign, and that the Surviving Rebells would perswade us we were now in a Fools Paradise, by reason of their New Utopian Common-Wealth, they were soon Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Holland</hi> by the Lord <hi>Gerard Scurph,</hi> who came with Commission from them, to Treat about a fair Correspondence and Commerce with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who were here kindly entertained, and not many Months after, some <hi>English</hi> Messengers sent over to perfect the same.</p>
            <p>Not long after happened the death of <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> brother-in-law to our now gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soveraign, a Prince whose Ancestors had ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well deserved of the <hi>Netherlandish</hi> State, though now former services began to be slighted, as when the Storm is one past, the danger is soon forgotten. His death was by his Widow the Princess <hi>Mary</hi> above all others very sorrowfully resented, who being left by him great with child, was within a little while after brought to bed of a Son, who was named after his Father, and is now living, the hopeful Heir of that Royal Family.</p>
            <p>And now our Mushrome Common-wealths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, though active enough for all mischief what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, yet began to look with an envious eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Dutch</hi> mens engrossing almost the whole Sea Trade to themselves, and therefore they framed an Act <hi>for the increase of Shipping, and the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99816:24"/>of Navigation.</hi> Which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending would be highly prejudicial to them in their way of Trade, they endeavoured with all their might, what by pleasing Messages, and what with Threats to get repeal'd; but seeing their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be in vain, they secretly meditated open hostility.</p>
            <p>The first Act whereof was on the 19. of <hi>May</hi> in the year 1652.
<note place="margin">See my <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies.</note> and began at first upon points of Honour at Sea; <hi>Van Trump</hi> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Admiral be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing toward <hi>Dover</hi> Road with two and forty Sail, refused to vail his Flag, a Ceremonial Honour, which the <hi>English</hi> appropriate to themselves, as being Lords of these Narrow Seas, in stead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hanging out his Red Flag, the usual signal of Defiance, and gave a broadside to <hi>Blake</hi> the <hi>English</hi> Admiral, whereupon a sharp fight ensued betwixt them, wherein the <hi>Dutch</hi> were worsted, losing in this fight one Ship which was sunk, and another of 30 Guns taken, with the Captains of both, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 150 Prisoners.</p>
            <p>This Action the States of <hi>Holland</hi> would not in any wise seem to own or countenance, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to excuse the matter, as done without their consent, they dispatched their Ambassadours into <hi>England,</hi> to renew the Treaty with the <hi>English</hi> Common-wealth, who though of the latter stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet would be accounted Superiour to the other. Yet notwithstanding these Overtures of Peace, the Treaty ended in an absolute breach: so that open War was denounced and publickly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamed on both sides.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:99816:25"/>
            <p>And first General <hi>Blake</hi> the <hi>English</hi> Admiral fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes twelve <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War towards the Isles of <hi>Orkney.</hi> Soon after Sir <hi>George Ayseough</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and set to guard the Narrow Seas with a Squadron of Ships, met with the <hi>Hollanders</hi> in the Road between <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and set upon their Fleet being 30 in number, of which 10 were taken and burnt, the rest hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly escaping by running a shore upon the Coast of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soon after happened another Encounter near <hi>Plymouth,</hi> between Sir <hi>George</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet, consisting of 60 Men of War, and 30 Merchants, part of the <hi>English</hi> Fleet coming up to Sir <hi>George Ayscoughs</hi> assistance. This Engagement continued very fierce till night parted them, not without some loss to the <hi>English,</hi> but much more to the <hi>Dutch.</hi> These successes were seconded by others very remarkable. General <hi>Blake</hi> steering North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, took six <hi>Holland</hi> Ships of a great value about the <hi>Downs.</hi> Captain <hi>Penn</hi> also took six more upon the Coast of <hi>France,</hi> as they were returning home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards from the <hi>Venetian</hi> Service, richly laden, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Men of War, of considerable burthens.</p>
            <p>Soon after (so great and deadly was their fewd) they were engaged again by General <hi>Blake</hi> on the back-side of <hi>Goodwin</hi> Sands, wherein the <hi>Dutch</hi> were lamentably defeated, which Bout was called the <hi>Kentish Knock.</hi> But in the <hi>Levant</hi> Seas, a small Fleet of the <hi>English,</hi> conveying certain Merchants men from <hi>Scanderoon,</hi> were set upon by 11
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99816:25"/>
               <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War; who over-powering them in number, took the <hi>Phoenix</hi> Friggot, and much dammaged the other. And afterwards about the beginning of <hi>December</hi> (their hatred being so great as to fight all Weathers) General <hi>Blake</hi> himself en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging with the whole Fleet of the <hi>Dutch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir R. Baker Contin.</note> was worsted, losing the <hi>Garland</hi> and <hi>Bonadventure,</hi> with some other Ships; and again in the <hi>Levant,</hi> Captain <hi>Badiley</hi> coming from <hi>Portolongone</hi> to the relief of C. <hi>Appleton,</hi> blockt up in the Mole of <hi>Legorn,</hi> was set upon by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> in which Engagement he lost three or four stout Ships.</p>
            <p>But one of the sharpest fights of all was near the <hi>Isle of Wight,</hi> and <hi>Portland,</hi> wherein the <hi>Dutch</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a great overthrow, 50 Merchants being taken 9 Men of War, above 2000 slain, and 1500 ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Prisoners.</p>
            <p>All these fights happened during the time the Long-Parliament (or rather the Rump or Fag end of them) ruled the Roast; but they having sate brooding a long time, and brought forth nothing but addle Eggs, <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> put them besides the Saddle, but not with an intent to ease the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Nation of their Tyranny, but onely to settle it in himself: and thereupon <hi>(Heavens protect us!)</hi> he was made Protector of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> because the Common-wealth being in its Infancy needed a Guardian. These Domestick Revolutions put new life into the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who well hoped from these distractions to gain a Victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>English,</hi> and therefore with great confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99816:26"/>put forth again to Sea, thinking: upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing so much as Chap-men for the <hi>English</hi> Fleet; saying,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Englands</hi> Worthies.</note>
               <hi>It was to be cryed out by the sound of Trumpets and Horns.</hi> But those who reckon without their Host, we say, must reckon twice; and the <hi>Dutch</hi> were deceived in their expectations; for coming to a fight on the North Fore-land, near unto the South Point of the <hi>Gober,</hi> (notwithstanding the <hi>English</hi> lost General <hi>Dean,</hi> one of their Admirals, who was slain by a great shot) yet received they a great overthrow, eleven Men of War, and two Water Hoys being taken, besides six Captains, sif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred Prisoners, and six Men of War, which were sunke.</p>
            <p>Certainly this War with the <hi>Dutch</hi> which had been driven on with so great success, might have been ended with as great advantages, by the Rump Parliament; and therefore <hi>Cromwel</hi> being scarce warm in his new seat, entertained their first Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Treaty, to which purpose they had sent Commissioners over into <hi>England.</hi> But whiles this was in doing, the <hi>Dutch</hi> (as it is thought) think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have taken our Navy napping, there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened a cruel fight betwixt them, the greatest du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all this War; wherein the <hi>Dutch</hi> whole Fleet was put to flight, about thirty Men of War sunk and fired, six Captains, and about a thousand Men taken Prisoners, and about six thousand slain, amongst whom (which added not a little to the greatness of the Victory) was their Admiral <hi>Van Trump,</hi> an expert Sea-man and good Souldier, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99816:26"/>one that would have been a Terrour to any but the <hi>English</hi> Nation. For this service Gold Chains were presented to the <hi>English</hi> Generals, <hi>Blake, Monk, Penn,</hi> and <hi>Lawson,</hi> and to the other Flag Captains; and silver Medals to the other Officers of the Fleet.</p>
            <p>No doubt no Nation under the Heavens have been more potent at Sea then the <hi>English,</hi> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at that present, but both before or since. I shall therefore after these <hi>Golgotha's</hi> of bloud, or Tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Relations, present you with a Copy of Verses made by a Laureat of our Nation, upon the puis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sance of our Navies, and the <hi>English</hi> Dominion at Sea.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Waller.</hi>
                  </note>Lords of the Worlds great waste, the Ocean, we</l>
               <l>Whole Forrests send to reign upon the Sea,</l>
               <l>And every Coast may trouble, or relieve,</l>
               <l>But none can visit us without our leave.</l>
               <l>Angels and We have this Prerogative,</l>
               <l>That none can at our happy Seat arrive:</l>
               <l>While we descend at pleasure, to in vade</l>
               <l>The bad with vengeance, or the good to aide.</l>
               <l>Our little World, the Image of the great,</l>
               <l>Like that amidst the boundlesse Ocean set,</l>
               <l>Of her own growth has all that Natures craves,</l>
               <l>And all thats rare as Tribute from the Waves:</l>
               <l>As <hi>Aegypt</hi> does not on the Clouds rely,</l>
               <l>But to her <hi>Nile</hi> ows more then to the Skye:</l>
               <l>So what our Earth, and what our Heaven denyes,</l>
               <l>Our ever constant friend, the Sea supplyes.</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99816:27"/>
               <l>The tast of hot <hi>Arabias</hi> spice we know</l>
               <l>Free from the scorching sun that makes it grow;</l>
               <l>Without the morn, in <hi>Persian</hi> Silks we shine,</l>
               <l>And without planting drink of every Vine;</l>
               <l>To dig for Wealth we weary not our limbs,</l>
               <l>Gold, though the heaviest mettall hither swims;</l>
               <l>Ours is the Harvest, where the <hi>Indians</hi> mow,</l>
               <l>We plow the Deep, and reap what others Sow.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But to return, This great Victory did not a little conduce to hasten the Conclusion of a Peace betwixt the two Nations, though on such terms (as one observes) more expedient for <hi>Cromwels</hi> present designes, then advantagious to the <hi>English</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>Now notwithstanding all this War, betwixt the two Nations, and the sad condition of our Exiled Sovereign by reason of the Potentness of the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in <hi>England:</hi> yet would not the <hi>Dutch</hi> be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to own his cause (though most just) Publickly; although to that purpose he sent the Lord <hi>Gerard</hi> Ambassadour to them, desiring them by a Letter Written to them with his own Hand, that he might have a Squadron of lusty Ships to bear his Flagg,
<note place="margin">Sir R. Baker Contin.</note> which he offered to Command himself as Admiral; Nor was his Royal Sister, the rincess of <hi>Orange,</hi> and several other of his Friends slack in the business, but what with the aversness of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Holland,</hi> (for the other Provinces seemed more inclinable to his desire) together with the Peace that ensued betwixt <hi>Cromwell</hi> and Them, he gained no more of them, notwithstanding his own
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99816:27"/>and his Friends so earnest Address, but only an Answer full of Complemental Civility to his Letter and Embassy.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> notwithstanding all Agreements would still be Trading, though in places where they were not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Articles, for which afterwards 18. of their Merchant Men were seized on at the <hi>Barbadoes</hi> by <hi>Penn</hi> and <hi>Venibles.</hi> And in this state stood the Affairs betwixt the two Nations, at such time as that Grand Tyrant <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> made an <hi>Exit</hi> off the Stage of this World: After which time they made a seeming complyance with our suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding new-fangled States-Men; neglecting and slighting the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and his Majesties Interest, untill such time as these Mushroms of State by their Ridiculous Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, had made way for his Majesties Happy Restauration; when (with the guide) they complied with the Current of Affairs as they then stood, Feasting and Entertaining him very Magnificently, and promising all Respects and Honour to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> whereupon his Majesty at his part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, from them, being ready to Embarque for <hi>England,</hi> said to them as followeth;
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>That he had so much kindness for them, that he would be jealous of them, if they gave a greater part of their Amity to any Prince then to him, seeing he loved them more then all the Princes beside, adding withall these words: <hi>Sirs, Whereas, I leave here in Your hands the Princess my Sister, and the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>Two Persons who are extreamly dear to me; I pray You, Sirs, take their interest to heart, and cause them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scent the Effects of the favour in the occasion which the Princesse my Sister shall request of You, either for her self, or the Prince her Son; Assuring You that all the Effects of Your Good Will shall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged of Me, as if I had Received them in my own Person.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Charles Rex.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>This was ordered to be Registered in the Records of the States General, and of the Province of <hi>Holland, In perpetuam rei memoriam.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:99816:28"/>
            <p>What the Transactions have been betwixt the two Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons since his Majesties Happy Restauration, and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the clashing which of late hath hapned, I shall not inlarge my self thereupon; Only, thus much let me tell ye, That our last Gallant Parliament so ill rescented their Injuries and Affronts done to our Nation, that they unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously Voted; <q rend="inline">That all obstructions of Trade should be removed; and particularly that the Injuries and Affronts done us by the <hi>Dutch</hi> should be inquired into, and reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died by all means possible, and that they would stand by his most Excellent Majesty in this inquiry and remedy, with their Lives and Fortunes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In pursuance of which Resolutions, Sir <hi>George Downing</hi> his Majesties Embassadour to that Nation, had several debates with them about it; The Lord <hi>Van-Gogh</hi> was also sent from them to his Sacred Majesty of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> who on <hi>Iuly</hi> 31. 1664. Delivered a Memorial unto his Majesty, in which, as also in his Majesties Answer, the principal grounds of the differences betwixt us being contained; I shall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore give you them both abreviated, so far as they concern our present businesse, wherein the Reader may see, how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous his Majesty hath been to maintain a firm Amity and Friendship with them, and to avoid (as much as in Honour he can) all Causes, which may conduce to a War betwixt the two Nations: The Sum of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ambassadours Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial, was this:</p>
            <p>That since it was evident, Vessels of War were preparing on both sides, which if they should go forth and meet at Sea, might by misunderstanding fall foule on each other; it was therefore desired his Majesty would be pleased to keep back his Fleet, as their Lordships offered on their part to do.</p>
            <p>That their Lordships were informed, that Captain <hi>Holmes</hi> with the Ships under his Command, had taken divers of their Vessels upon the Coast of <hi>Affrick,</hi> and also made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self Master of <hi>Capo Verde,</hi> and some other Forts belonging
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99816:28"/>to them, contrary to the Last Treaty; They therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Restitution of the same, and Reparations of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages suffered thereby.</p>
            <p>That their Lordships being each day confirmed, not only of the foresaid Action of Captain <hi>Holmes,</hi> but that he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a further Prosecution of his Designe, by seizing on all the Coast, expecting a supply of Ships from <hi>England;</hi> That therefore his Majesty would be Intreated to Command the said Captain <hi>Holmes,</hi> and those who were in that Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to restore the foresaid Forts and Vessels, and to repair the damages suffered thereby; As also, by express command to prohibit those Ships, which by report, are now ready to set Saile, or which may be fitting for that purpose.</p>
            <p>And lastly, considering that those Vessels which come from the United Provinces into the several Streams of this Kingdome, are there stopped under pretence of Persons and Commodities on board, which come from places infected with the Plague, or suspected so to be, to the obstruction of Trade, and prejudice of both Nations; The said Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour therefore insisted, that the same might be remedied, or at least the strictness of those orders mittigated in such mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure as should by reason be found convenient, since by the mercy of God, all the Provinces in general, were not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the Contagion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majesties Answer was to this Effect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That concerning the Preparations and Provissions of Vessels of War, it was well known, there was order given in the beginning of the Year, for providing a less Guard of Ships for this Summer, then any Year since his Happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stauration, believing he might well save that charge, being in so good Intelligence with all his Neighbours. Until the Parliament upon the whole Nations Cry, pressed him to take an extraordinary way to repair the people for the daily injuries they sustained from the <hi>Dutch</hi> by depredations at
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99816:29"/>Sea, in other places, as well as in the <hi>East-Indies,</hi> wherein were some circumstances of that presumption, by declaring their Dominion, and inhibiting Commerce against the Law of Nations: To whom his Majesty made no other Answer, but that he doubted not the States of the United Provinces would cause Justice to be done, and to that end, appointed his Minister to make a representation and complaint, for which (considering the nature of the Offences) he expected thanks for them, but contrarily they gave order for the present setting out of a very great Number of Ships of War, no other visible cause being manifest, then to declare to the world how they defied both him and his Parliament: So that it would have been very little to his Honour or Interest, if he likewise had not prepared a considerable Fleet for his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and being thus prepared, it would be a very strange proposition to be kept still within the Ports, and that it would be found by their demeanour, that their instructions were not to injure our Friends, but to defend him and his Subjects from receiving injuries of Enemies.</p>
            <p>As therefore he had with an everlasting manifestation of his Affection and Kindness to the United Provinces, concluded the late Treaty, by which many memorable injuries to him and his people, (particularly that of <hi>Amboyna</hi>) were put in Oblivion; So he had for his part exactly observed every Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, and had no sooner been moved in any particular wherein the Subjects of the United Provinces were grieved, but that speedy order was given for their redress, without putting them to those formalities which are usual in Courts of Justice; whereas contrarily, when his Minister had made complaints at the <hi>Hague,</hi> notwithstanding the matter of Fact were most notorious, yet was not redress given to any one, and such delayes used in all, as was upon the matter a plaine denyal of Justice, which caused great complaints from his Subjects every day; Yet for all this, he had not granted one Letter of Mart upon the Subjects of that State.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:99816:29"/>
            <p>That concerning Captain <hi>Holmes,</hi> he had no Commission to take <hi>Capo Verde,</hi> or any other place belonging to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> or to act any hostility against them, but what was for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his Subjects, and their Trade in those Parts; and therefore expected his Declaration should have found more credit with them then informations of Seamen, who seldom know what they informe: That upon Captain <hi>Holmes</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, who was expected every day; a due enquiry should be made, and a just determination done; That the Ships design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for those Parts at present, had neither Power nor Will to wrong the Subjects of that State. But on the contrary, his Majesty was sorry to hear, not from general Rumour, but pregnant Evidence of his Governour of the Fort of <hi>Corman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> that about the end of last <hi>January,</hi> the Commanders of the Ships belonging to the <hi>Dutch VVest-India</hi> Company, after divers Assaults and Restraints of his Merchant Ships in those Seas, they hired the King of <hi>Fantine</hi> to Assault and Surprize his Castle of <hi>Cormantine,</hi> and to deliver it to them for the price of Sixty <hi>Bendys,</hi> whereof one half was by them paid down, with further condition that the Natives should enjoy the Plunder of the Castle; To perform which, the said <hi>Dutch</hi> Commanders supplyed the King of <hi>Fantine</hi> with a great quantity of Musquets, Powder and Cartages; whereof his Commander having notice, by the assistance of God surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed the same, which perhaps was one of those Acts of Hosti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity mentioned in the Memorial, no Intelligence coming of any other. Two <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War came from the <hi>Mina</hi> to <hi>Cape</hi> Coast to attend this Enterprize at the appointed time; and accordingly, the King of <hi>Fantine, Feb.</hi> 5. came with 500 Men to have surprized the Castle, but finding himself discovered, was forced to retire with some loss; the next day he advanced again with a Body of 3000 Men, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a sharp Fight with the <hi>English</hi> for the space of four hours, but was beat off with great loss, since which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the motives and contract aforesaid; The <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships at the same time driving a small <hi>English</hi> Ship under the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99816:30"/>Command of Captain <hi>Borthwick</hi> into his Majesties Port of <hi>Inashange,</hi> Anchored by him, hindred all the Cances from coming on board him, and took his Boat and five Men, which they would not restore, till they had knowledge their other enterprize was miscarried. This his Majesty doubted not, they would in manifestation of this perfideous designe cause Exemplary Justice to be inflicted on the persons guilty of it; and instead of sending Ships of War to justifie those proceedings (which might produce a War betwixt the Two Nations) would warn their <hi>VVest-India</hi> Company hereafter to forbear such Out-rages, and not to presume under the stile of Merchants to Usurp the Prerogative of Princes, and Assume such a Dominion to themselves, which if they were Invested with, would not warrant them to inhabit Traffique and Commerce with their Neighbours, but must incense all Christian Princes against their Presumption.</p>
            <p>That his Majesty was greatly Afflicted for the Visitation of God upon them, by which means the Commerce of both Nations was suspended; but that it could not be expected he should decline from that provident care of his People, in using all possible means to preserve them from that conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which without such restraints could not be; and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the goodness of God would shortly put a period to it, and make the Correspondence as safe and wholesome as it had been.</p>
            <p>That He desired their Ambassadour to assure them, that he was firmly resolved to maintain a firm Amity &amp; Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with them, that (by the Blessing of God) a War could not fall out betwixt them, unless they departed from all Rules of Justice, and suffered their Subjects to involve them in a War, to support the wrong they did their Neighbours against all right, which he hoped their great Wisedomes would prevent.</p>
            <p>By this which hath been said, the Reader may easily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture how the Affairs stand at present betwixt the two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and with what prudence and sincerity his Majesties
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99816:30"/>proceedings hath been towards them. I shall not insist to amplifie any further therein; Onely now at last, as a Coral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary to the whole, considering the chief Affairs of <hi>Holland</hi> have their dependence upon the Princes of <hi>Orange:</hi> I shall give you a Brief Account and Character of them, from their first investiture into that Principality, unto this present time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1475. King <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France</hi> invested <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> with the Principality of <hi>Orange;</hi> who dying, left his Estate and Government to his Heroick, Active, Successive <hi>William,</hi> whose Magnificent Prowess was so Considerable, that <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11 desired his Alliance, and gave him his own Cousin in Marriage, Esteeming him for a most Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous Person all the dayes of his life.</p>
            <p>His Honour and Estate being much Improved, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed the same to <hi>John Chabon,</hi> a Prince of admirable Valour, whose Puissance <hi>France</hi> dreaded, and whom the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> found a Loving Friend, in whose Service he died, <hi>Anno</hi> 1496.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philibert Chabon</hi> his Nephew, was Heir to his Estate and Authority; a Gallant Souldier, and of a Noble Resolution, who continued a True and Constant Servant to the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> who dying without Issue, the Honour of <hi>Nassaw</hi> was interwoven with the Magnificent Glory of the House of <hi>Orange; Philiberts</hi> Sister being Married to <hi>Rene Nassaw,</hi> whose Son <hi>Henry</hi> is by <hi>Philibert</hi> Adopted for his Heir, 1500.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Henry</hi> as he was Heir to his Estate, so was he to his Virtues, being bred a Souldier from his Cradle, his Blood Ennobling his Name and his Actions his Blood. He per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed many Gallant services for the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and died before <hi>Luxemburght;</hi> being said to have left six things behind him of great Consequence to <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Flanders:</hi> 1. How to Entrench and Fortifie double. 2. How to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat safely. 3. How to Embattle the Foot four deep se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely. 4. How to bear a charge, and return it home un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntedly. 5. How to tire an Army with often surprizals,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99816:31"/>And 6. How to conquer with kindness. He died, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1544.</p>
            <p>To whom by his Will and the Peoples Vote Succeeded his Cousin <hi>William,</hi> a Martiall Prince, and who was bred up in the School of <hi>Mars,</hi> under Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> in the Wars of <hi>Germany;</hi> a Person very Honourable in his Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session in <hi>France,</hi> Noble in <hi>Germany,</hi> and Rich in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> a Popular Prince, Wise, Wary, Eloquent of Speech, and Grave in Councel, and of a Plausible Carriage and Behaviour, of whom it was questionable whether he were more able in comprehending business, or more wary in meanaging it. Under this Prince the <hi>Netherlanders</hi> threw off their subjection to the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> as we declared to you in the beginning of the History; He was at last basely Murthered by one <hi>Balthazar Gerard,</hi> being shot to Death as he came from Dinner; a most Wise, Constant, Magnanimious Prince, his Motto being, <hi>Mediis tranquillus inundis,</hi> </p>
            <p>Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> being of the age of 17 years, succeeded him in his Honours and Estate, he brought the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to a Peace, the <hi>English</hi> to a League, and his own People to a Peaceable submission to his Government; and so died in the bed of Honour.</p>
            <p>Count <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Nassaw</hi> succeeded him, a Great States-Man, but in the midst of his designes he dyed, leaving his Honours and Estate to his Son Prince <hi>William,</hi> that Married the Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> Daughter to our late Martyred Soveraign King <hi>Charles,</hi> who dying in the Prime of his years, left his Honours and Title to his Son <hi>William,</hi> who is now living, a most hopefull Prince, whom <hi>Holland</hi> is jealous of, and hath been uncivill to, considering his Great Ancestours Merrit and Service, though we make no doubt, but he will attain by his Deserts, to no less Power and Grandeur, then any of his Renowned Predecessours.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99816:31"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>